<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse about tradition shewing what is meant by it, and what tradition is to be received, and what tradition is to be rejected.</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7194</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12588072</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12588072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63802</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56650)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63802)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 674:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse about tradition shewing what is meant by it, and what tradition is to be received, and what tradition is to be rejected.</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>54, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Miles Flesher for Robert Horne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Simon Patrick, Bishop of Ely. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Tradition (Theology)</term>
               <term>Authority.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63802:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63802:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE ABOUT TRADITION; Shewing what is meant by it, AND WHAT TRADITION Is to be received, AND WHAT TRADITION Is to be rejected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Miles Fleſher,</hi> for
<hi>Robert Horne,</hi> at the South Entrance of the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Fincham Gardiner,</hi> at the <hi>White Horſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate Street,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:63802:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63802:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE ABOUT TRADITION.</head>
            <p>AN obligation being laid upon us at our Baptiſm, to believe and to doe the whole will of God, revealed unto us by Chriſt Jeſus; it concerns every one that would be ſaved, to enquire where that whole, intire will of God is to be found? where he may ſo certainly meet with it, and be ſo informed about it, that he may reſt ſatisfied he hath it all?</p>
            <p>And there would be no difficulty in this matter, had not the worldly intereſts of ſome men, raiſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies about it; and made that intricate and perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which, in it ſelf, is eaſie and plain. For the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſal of the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> at Baptiſm, and of that alone; as a Summary of that Faith, whoſe ſincere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion intitles us to the Grace there conferred; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in its VI. Article, that the <hi>Holy Scripture containeth all things neceſſary to Salvation; ſo that whatſoever is not read therein, nor may be proved thereby, is not to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of any man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63802:3"/>of Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this ſtrikes off ſo many of the Doctrines of the preſent Roman Church, which are not to be found in the Scripture, nor have any countenance there; that they are forced to ſay: <hi>the faith once delivered to the Saints</hi> (mentioned by S. <hi>Jude</hi>) is not intirely delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Scripture; but we muſt ſeek for the reſt in the Traditions of the Church. Which Traditions, ſay they, are to be received as a part of the Rule of Faith, with the ſame Religious reverence that we do the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture.</p>
            <p>Now, though this is not really the bottom of their hearts (as will appear before I have done) but they finally reſt for their ſatisfaction in matters of Faith ſomewhere elſe; yet this being plauſibly pretended by them, in their own juſtification, that they follow Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; and in their accuſations of us, that we forſake Tradition: I ſhall briefly let all our people ſee, who are not willing to be deceived, what they are to judge and ſay in this buſineſs of Tradition. About which a great noiſe is made, as if we durſt not ſtand to it, and as if they of the Roman Church ſtedfaſtly kept it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any variation: neither of which is true, I ſhall plainly ſhew in this ſhort Diſcourſe.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The meaning of the word.</head>
               <p>Which for clearneſs ſake ſhall begin with the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the word TRADITION: which in Engliſh is no more than <hi>delivering</hi> unto another; and by a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure ſignifies, <hi>the matter which is delivered;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians <hi>the Doctrine of our Religion</hi> delivered to us. And there being two ways of delivering Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines to us, either by
<hi>writing</hi> or by <hi>word of mouth;</hi> 
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63802:3"/>it ſignifies either of them indifferently: the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as you ſhall ſee preſently, being <hi>Traditions.</hi> But cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome hath determined this word to the laſt of theſe ways, and diſtinguiſhed <hi>Tradition</hi> from <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or writings: at leaſt from the Holy Writings; and made it ſignifie that which is not delivered in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or writings. For though the Scripture be Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition alſo, and the very firſt
<hi>Tradition,</hi> and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all true and legitimate Antiquity; yet in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon language <hi>Traditions</hi> now are ſuch ancient Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, as are conveyed to us ſome other way: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by word of mouth, as ſome will have it, from one generation to another; or by humane Writings, which are not of the ſame authority with the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to judge of them.</head>
               <p>Now there is no better way to judge aright of ſuch Traditions, than by conſidering theſe <hi>four</hi> things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, The Authours of them, whence they come.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, The matter of them.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, Their Authority.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, The means by which we come to know, they derive themſelves from ſuch Authours, as they pretend unto: and conſequently have any authority, to demand admiſſion into our belief.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. For the Firſt of theſe, every body knows and confeſſes, that all Traditions ſuppoſe ſome <hi>Authour,</hi> from whom they originally come, and who is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer of thoſe Doctrines to Chriſtian people: who being told by the preſent Church, or any perſon in it; that ſuch and ſuch Doctrines are to be received, though
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63802:4"/>not contained in the Holy Scriptures, becauſe they are
<hi>Traditions;</hi> ought in Conſcience to inquire from whom thoſe
<hi>Traditions</hi> come, or who firſt delivered them: By which means they will be able to judge, what credit is to be given to them, when it is once cleared to them, from what Authours they really come. Now whatſoever is delivered to us in Chriſtianity, comes either from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or from his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or from the <hi>Church</hi> (either in General, or in part) or from pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>Doctours</hi> in the Church. There is nothing now called a Tradition in the Chriſtian World, but proceeds from one or from all of theſe four Originals.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And the matter which they deliver to us, (which is next to be conſidered) is either concerning that <hi>Faith,</hi> and godly life, which is neceſſary to Salvation; or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Opinions, Rites, Ceremonies, Cuſtoms,</hi> and things belonging to Order. Both which, as I ſaid, may be conveyed either by writing or without writing; by the Divine writings, or by humane writings: though theſe two ways are not alike certain.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Now it is evident to every underſtanding, that things of both ſorts which are delivered to us, have their <hi>Authority,</hi> from the Credit of the <hi>Authour</hi> from whence they firſt come. If that be Divine, their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is Divine; if it be onely Humane, their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity can be no more. And among Humane Authours, if their credit be great, the authority of what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver is great; if it be little, its authority is little: and accordingly muſt be accepted with greater or leſſer reverence.</p>
               <p>Upon which ſcore whatſoever can be made to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to come from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it hath the higheſt authority, and ought to be received with abſolute ſubmiſſion to it, becauſe he is the Son of God. And likewiſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever appears to have been delivered by the
<hi>Apoſtles</hi> 
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63802:4"/>in his name, hath the ſame Authority: they being his Miniſters, ſent by Him, as He was by God the Father; and indued with a Divine Power, which atteſted unto them. In like manner, whatſoever is delivered by the <hi>Church,</hi> hath the ſame Authority which the Church hath: which though it be not equal to the foregoing (the Church having no ſuch Divine Power, nor infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible judgment, as the Apoſtles had) yet is of ſuch weight and moment, that it ought to be reverenced next to theirs. I mean, the ſenſe of the whole Church; which muſt be acknowledged alſo to be of greater or leſſer Authority, as it was nearer, or farther off from the times of the Apoſtles. What was delivered by their immediate followers, ought to weigh ſo much with us, as to have the greateſt humane Authority; and to be look'd upon as little leſs than Divine. The Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal conſent of the next Generation, is an Authority ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching as near to the former, as the Ages do one to another. But what is delivered in latter times hath leſs humane Authority, though pretending to come, but without proof, from more early days: and hath no Authority at all, if it contradict the ſenſe of the Church, when it was capable to be better acquainted with the mind of Chriſt, and of his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>As for particular Churches, their Authority ought to be reverenced by every member of them; when they profeſs to deliver ſincerely the ſenſe of the Church Univerſal; and when they determine, as they have power to do, Controverſies of Faith, or decree Rites and Ceremonies (not contrary to God's word) in which enery one ought to acquieſce.</p>
               <p>But we cannot ſay the ſame of that which comes from any
<hi>private Doctour</hi> in the Church, modern or Ancient: which can have no greater Authority than he himſelf was of; but is more or leſs credible, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63802:5"/>as he was more or leſs diligent, knowing, and ſtrictly religious.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But to all this, it is neceſſary that it do ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, that ſuch Doctrines do really come from thoſe Authours, whoſe <hi>Traditions</hi> they pretend to be. This is the great, and the onely, thing; about which there is any queſtion, among ſober and judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. How to be ſufficiently aſſured, that any thing which is not delivered unto us in the Scriptures, doth certainly come; for inſtance, from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or his holy <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> For in this all Chriſtians are agreed, that whatſoever was delivered by Chriſt, from God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or by the Apoſtles from Chriſt, is to be embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and firmly retained, whether it be written or not written: that makes no difference at all, if we can be certain it came from Him, or them. For what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Holy Scripture, hath not its Authority, becauſe it is written: but becauſe it came from God. If Chriſt ſaid a thing, it is enough: we ought to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto it: but we muſt firſt know that he ſaid it; and let the means of knowing it be what they will, if we can certainly know He ſaid it, we yield to it.</p>
               <p>But how we can be certain (at this diſtance of time, from his being in the world) that any thing, now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to it, was ſaid by Chriſt, which is not recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in the Holy Scriptures; there is the buſineſs. And it is a matter of ſuch importance, that it cannot be expected any man ſhould be ſatisfied without very good evidence of it: but he may very reaſonably que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether many things be not falſly aſcribed unto Him, and unto his Apoſtles; which never came from them. Nay, whether thoſe things, which are affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be the Doctrines of the Primitive Church, and of the whole Church, be not of ſome later Original; and of ſome particular Church, or private Doctours in <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63802:5"/>the Church: unto whoſe Authority that reverence is not due, which ought to be paid, and which we wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly give unto the former.</p>
               <p>Now according to this ſtate of the matter, any good Chriſtian among us (who is deſirous to know the Truth, and to preſerve himſelf from Errour) may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcern what <hi>Traditions</hi> ought to be received, and held faſt; and what we are not bound unto, without any alteration; and what are not to be received at all, but to be rejected; and how far thoſe things are from being credible, which the Roman Church now would obtrude upon us, under the name of Apoſtolical, or ancient Traditions; without any Authority from the Holy Scriptures, or (in truth) any Authority but their own, and ſome private Doctours, whoſe opinions can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not challenge an abſolute ſubmiſſion to them.</p>
               <p>But to give every one, that would be rightly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, fuller ſatisfaction in this buſineſs; I ſhall not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf with this General Diſcourſe: but ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and diſtinctly ſhew what
<hi>Traditions</hi> we own, and heartily receive; and then what
<hi>Traditions</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not own, but with good reaſon refuſe. Theſe ſhall be the two Parts of this ſhort Treatiſe: wherein I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour that our people may be inſtructed not merely to reject Errours, but alſo to affirm the Truth.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63802:6"/>
            <head>PART I. <hi>What</hi> Traditions <hi>we receive.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. AND in the firſt place we acknowledge that what is now
<hi>holy Scripture,</hi> was once onely <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition;</hi> properly ſo called: that is Doctrine by word of mouth. In this we all agree, I ſay, that the whole Goſpel or Doctrine of Chriſt, which is now upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in thoſe Books, we call the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> was once unwritten, when it was firſt preached by our bleſſed Saviour, and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Which muſt be noted to remove that ſmall Objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with which they of the Roman Church are wont to trouble ſome peoples minds, merely from the Name of <hi>Traditions:</hi> which Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtles, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires thoſe to whom he writes, carefully to obſerve. Particularly in that famous place: 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> II. 15. where we find this exhortation, <hi>Therefore, Brethren, ſtand faſt, and hold the Traditions, which ye have been taught, whether by word, or our Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold, ſay they, here are things not written, but delivered by word of mouth; which the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> are commanded to hold. Very true, (ſhould the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our Church ſay, to thoſe that inſiſt upon this) but, behold alſo, we beſeech you, <hi>what</hi> the Traditions are of which the Apoſtle here writes; and mark alſo <hi>when</hi> it was that they were partly unwritten.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:63802:6"/>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, it is manifeſt that he means by
<hi>Traditions,</hi> the Doctrines which we now reade in the holy Scriptures. For the very firſt word <hi>therefore</hi> is an indication that this verſe is an inference, from what he had ſaid in the foregoing. Now the things he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore treated of, are the grand Doctrines of the Goſpel, or the way of Salvation revealed unto us by Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, from God the Father: who
<hi>hath from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> (ſaith he, v. 13. 14.) <hi>choſen you to Salvation, through ſanctification of the Spirit, and belief of the truth, whereunto he hath called you,</hi> &amp;c. This is the ſum of the Goſpel: and whatſoever he had delivered unto them about theſe matters, of their
<hi>ſanctification,</hi> or of their <hi>faith,</hi> or of their
<hi>ſalvation,</hi> by <hi>obtaining the glory of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (to which they were choſen, and called, through their ſanctification, and faith) this he exhorts them to hold faſt; whether it was contained in this Epiſtle, or in his former preaching: for he had not occaſion now to write all that he had formerly delivered by word of mouth.</p>
            <p>Which afterward was put in writing: for mark (which is the ſecond thing) the time <hi>when</hi> ſome things remained unwritten; which was, when this Epiſtle was ſent to the <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi> Then ſome things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their ſalvation, were not contained in this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but, <hi>as yet,</hi> delivered onely by word of mouth unto <hi>this Church.</hi> I ſay, to <hi>this Church;</hi> for it doth not follow, that all Churches whatſoever, were, at the time of the writing of this Epiſtle, without the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpel completely written; becauſe among the
<hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> ſome Traditions or Doctrines were as yet unwritten. Which can in reaſon be extended no farther than to themſelves, and to this Epiſtle; which did not contain all the Evangelical Doctrine, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writings, which it is poſſible were then extant in ſome other Churches, did.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:63802:7"/>
            <p>And, I ſay, <hi>as yet</hi> unwritten in that Church; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> no doubt, had afterward more communicated to them in writing, beſides this Epiſtle, or the former either; <hi>viz.</hi> all the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> and the <hi>Acts</hi> of Apoſtles, and other
<hi>Apoſtolical Epiſtles,</hi> which we now enjoy. Which <hi>writings,</hi> we may be confident, contain the Traditions, which the Apoſtle had delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the <hi>Theſſalonians, by word:</hi> concerning the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, Birth, Life, Miracles, Death, Reſurrection,</hi> and <hi>Aſcention</hi> of our bleſſed Saviour; and concerning the <hi>coming of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the <hi>miſſion of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles:</hi> and all the reſt which is there recorded for our everlaſting inſtruction.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is in vain to argue from this place, that there are ſtill, at this day, ſome <hi>unwritten Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> which we are to follow: unleſs the Apoſtle had ſaid, <hi>hold the Traditions which ye have been taught by word, which ſhall never be written.</hi> And it is in vain for us to enquire after any ſuch Traditions, or to rely upon them when they are offered unto us: unleſs we were ſure, that there was ſomething, neceſſary to our Salvation, delivered in their Sermons, which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be delivered in writing; and unleſs we knew where to find it, as certainly, as we do that which they have committed to writing.</p>
            <p>And it is to no more purpoſe to ſhew us the word
<hi>Tradition,</hi> in other places of Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s writings: par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in the <hi>III.</hi> Chapter of the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>v.</hi>
6. where, by <hi>Tradition,</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> underſtands the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's <hi>Example,</hi> which he had given them; and ſo it follows,
<hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>for your ſelves know, how you ought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us,</hi> &amp;c. or it may refer to the <hi>commandment</hi> he had given them in his former Epiſtle <hi>IV.</hi> 11. (which the Reader may be pleaſed to compare with this) but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with any colour be expounded to ſignifie any Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63802:7"/>of Faith, about which the Roman Church now contends with us. For it is plain, it hath reſpect to their good manners, and orderly living: for the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of which we need go no whither, but to the holy Scriptures; wherein we are taught fully enough, how we ought to walk, and pleaſe God in all things.</p>
            <p>The ſame may be ſaid of that place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> XI. 2.
<hi>Now I praiſe you, Brethren, that you remember me in all things, and keep the Traditions</hi> (or <hi>Ordinances,</hi> as we render it, or
<hi>Precepts,</hi> as the Vulgar Latin it ſelf hath it) <hi>as I delivered them unto you.</hi> For we are ſo obſervant of what he hath delivered, that we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> were now alive, and in this Church, he would <hi>praiſe</hi> us (as he doth the <hi>Corinthians</hi>) for
<hi>keeping the Traditions, as he delivered them;</hi> and on the contrary reprove and condemn the Roman Church, for not keeping them, as they were firſt delivered. And we have good ground for this confidence: there being an inſtance in that very Chapter, which demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates our fidelity in preſerving the very firſt Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and their unfaithfulneſs in letting them go. For he tells us, <hi>v.</hi> 23. that he had <hi>delivered to them, what he had received of the Lord:</hi> and that which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and delivered, was about the <hi>whole Communion</hi> (as you may reade there and in the following verſes, 24, 25.) in both kinds; the <hi>Cup,</hi> as well as the <hi>Bread.</hi> Thus, he ſaith, the Lord appointed it, and thus he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it: and this <hi>Tradition</hi> we keep intire, as he
<hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> it of the Lord, and <hi>delivered</hi> it to his Church, in this Epiſtle; which is a part of the holy Scripture: whereas they do not keep it, but have broken this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Tradition, and give the Communion of Chriſt's Body and Bloud otherwiſe than Saint <hi>Paul</hi> delivered, keeping the Cup from the people.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:63802:8"/>
            <p>By which I deſire all, that love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity, to judge which Church keeps cloſeſt to the <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition</hi> (for ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Communion in both kinds; that which he <hi>delivered,</hi> or left as a
<hi>Tradition</hi> with them) they that ſtick to what is unqueſtionably the Apoſtolical Doctrine, or they that leave it, to follow thoſe Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines (or preſumptions rather) which at the beſt, are very dubious and uncertain?</p>
            <p>And farther, I deſire all that reade this Paper, to conſider, whether it be reaſonable to think that thoſe Rites, which have no Authority in the holy Scripture (but were inſtituted perhaps by the Apoſtles) have been kept pure and uncorrupted; according to their firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: when thoſe ſacred Rites (for inſtance the <hi>holy Euchariſt</hi>) are not preſerved intire, which are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ordained in the holy Writings.</p>
            <p>And ſo much may ſerve for the firſt thing: for it would be too long, to explain all the reſt of the places of holy Scripture, which they are wont to alledge (though the word <hi>Tradition</hi> be not mentioned in them) to give a colour to their preſent pretences: How per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently, may be judged by theſe places now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly</hi> then, That word of God which was once unwritten, being now written; we acknowledge our ſelves to be much indebted to the Church of God in all foregoing Ages, which hath preſerved the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and delivered them down to us, as his word: which we ought to do unto thoſe that ſhall ſucceed us; as our Church teacheth us in its Twentieth Article: where the Church is affirmed to be <hi>a Witneſs and a keeper of holy Writ.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63802:8"/>
            <p>This <hi>Tradition</hi> we own; it being univerſal, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, uninterrupted, and undenied. Though, in truth, this is <hi>Tradition</hi> in another ſenſe of the word; not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the Doctrine delivered unto us, but the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and means of its delivery.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if any member of our Church be preſſed by thoſe of the Romiſh perſuaſion, with this Argument, for their preſent
<hi>Traditions,</hi> that Scripture it ſelf is come to us by
<hi>Tradition,</hi> let them anſwer thus: Very right, it is ſo, and we thank God for it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let this be no part of our diſpute; it being a thing preſuppoſed in all diſcourſes about Religion, a thing agreed among all Chriſtian people, that we reade the word of God when we reade the holy Scriptures. Which being delivered to us, and accepted by us as his word; we ſee no neceſſity of any other Tradition or Doctrine, which is not to be found there, or cannot be proved from thence: for they tell us, they are able to make, even the men of God, wiſe unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And if they preſs you again and ſay, how do you know that ſome Books are Canonical and others not; is it not by a conſtant Tradition? Anſwer them again in this manner: Yes, this is true alſo, and would to God, you would ſtand to this univerſal Tradition; and receive no other Books, but what have been ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. But know withall, that this <hi>univerſal Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Books of Scripture (unto which you have added ſeveral Apocryphal Writings, which have not been conſtantly delivered, as thoſe we receive) is no part of the <hi>Tradition or Doctrine delivered.</hi> That is, no Doctrine diſtinct from the Scriptures; but onely the inſtrument or means of conveying that Doctrine unto us.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63802:9"/>
            <p>In ſhort, it is the fidelity of the Church with whom the Canon of Scripture was depoſed: but is no more a Doctrine, not written in the Scripture; than the Tradition or delivery of the <hi>Code,</hi> or Book of the
<hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law,</hi> is any opinion or Law not written in that
<hi>Code.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we are more aſſured of the fidelity of the Church herein, than the Civilians can be aſſured of the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their predeceſſours in preſerving and delivering the Books of their Law to them: becauſe theſe holy Books were always kept with a greater care, than any other Books whatſoever; and in the acceptance of them alſo, we find there was great caution uſed, that they might not be deceived: all Chriſtians looking upon them to be of ſuch importance, that all Religion, they thought, was concerned in them.</p>
            <p>Of which this is an Argument, that they who ſought to deſtroy the Chriſtian Religion, in the primitive times, ſought nothing more than to deſtroy the Bible. Which they were wont to demand, of thoſe who were ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be Chriſtians, to be delivered up to them; that they might burn it. And according as men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved themſelves in this trial, ſo they were reputed to be Chriſtians, or not Chriſtians. And the
<hi>Traditours,</hi> as they were called; that is, they who delivered the holy Scriptures into the hands of the Pagans; were look'd upon by Chriſtians as men that were content to part with their Religion. For which there could be no reaſon; but that they thought Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be therein contained; and to be betrayed by thoſe who delivered them to be burnt.</p>
            <p>By which I have proved more than I intended, in this part of my Diſcourſe; that in the holy Scriptures, the whole will of God concerning our Salvation, is contained. Which is the true Queſtion between us and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63802:9"/>the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> Not whether the Scripture be delivered to us as the word of God, or no, (in this our people ought to tell them we are all agreed) but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have been delivered, as the whole will of God. And from that argument now mentioned and many more, we conclude that Univerſal Tradition ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving directed us unto theſe Books and no other: they direct us ſufficiently, without any other Doctrines, unto God, and to our everlaſting reſt.</p>
            <p>And if they urge you farther, and ſay, that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry credit of the Scripture depends upon Tradition: tell them that it is a ſpeech not to be endured, if they mean thereby that it gives the Scripture its authority (and if they mean leſs, we are agreed, as hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid) for it is to ſay, that Man gives authority to God's Word. Whereas in truth, the holy Scriptures are not therefore of Divine Authority; becauſe the Church hath delivered them ſo to be: but the Church hath delivered them ſo to be, becauſe it knew them to be of ſuch authority. And if the Church ſhould have conceived, or taught otherwiſe, of theſe Writings, than as of the undoubted Oracles of God; ſhe would have erred damnably, in ſuch a Tradition.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſum up what hath been ſaid in this <hi>ſecond</hi> particular, in a few words. Chriſt and his Apoſtles at firſt taught the Church by word of mouth; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that which they preached was by the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God committed to writing, and delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, to be the ground of our Faith. Which is no more than <hi>Irenaeus</hi> hath ſaid in expreſs words. (<hi>L.</hi> III. <hi>C.</hi> 1.) ſpeaking of them by whom the Goſpel came into all Nations: <hi>which they then preached, but afterward, by the will of God delivered unto us in the Scriptures; to be, in time to come, the foundation and pillar of our Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63802:10"/>
            <p n="3">III. And farther we likewiſe acknowledge that the ſum and ſubſtance of the Chriſtian Religion, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scriptures, hath been delivered down to us, even from the Apoſtles days, in other ways, or forms, beſides the Scriptures. For inſtance, in the <hi>Baptiſmal Vow;</hi> in the <hi>Creed;</hi> in the <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>Hymns</hi> of the Church. Which we may call <hi>Traditions,</hi> if we pleaſe: but they bring down to us no new Doctrine; but onely deliver, in an abridgment, the ſame Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which we find in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Upon this there is no need that I ſhould enlarge: but I proceed farther to affirm,</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That we reverently receive alſo the unanimous
<hi>Tradition</hi> or Doctrine of the Church in all ages, which determines the
<hi>meaning</hi> of the holy Scripture; and makes it more clear and unqueſtionable in any point of Faith, wherein we can find it hath declared its ſenſe. For we look upon this <hi>Tradition</hi> as nothing elſe but the <hi>Scripture unfolded:</hi> not a new thing, which is not in the Scripture; but the Scripture explained and made more evident.</p>
            <p>And thus ſome part of the <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> may be called a
<hi>Tradition;</hi> as it hath expreſly delivered unto us the ſenſe of the Church of God, concerning that great Article of our Faith; that Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>the Son of God.</hi> Which they teach us was always thus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; the Son of God, <hi>begotten of his Father before all worlds, and of the ſame ſubſtance with the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Tradition ſuppoſes the Scripture for its ground; and delivers nothing but what the Fathers, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Nice,</hi> believed to be contained there; and was firſt fetch'd from thence. For we find in <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret (L.</hi> I. <hi>C.</hi> 6.) that the famous Emperour
<hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> 
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63802:10"/>admoniſhed thoſe Fathers, in all their queſtions and debates to conſult onely with theſe heavenly inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Writings: <hi>becauſe the Evangelical, and Apoſtolical Books, and the Oracles of the old Prophets, do evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtruct us what to think in Divine matters.</hi> This is ſo clear a Teſtimony, that in thoſe days, they made this the complete Rule of their Faith, whereby they ended Controverſies (which was the reaſon that in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Synods we find they were wont to lay the Bible before them) and that there is nothing in the
<hi>Nicene Creed,</hi> but what is to be found in the Bible; that Cardinal
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath nothing to reply to it, but this: <hi>Conſtantine was indeed a great Emperour, but no great Doctour.</hi> Which is rather a ſcoff, than an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: and caſts a ſcorn not onely upon him, but upon that great Council, who, as the ſame <hi>Theodoret,</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, aſſented unto that Speech of <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> So it there follows in theſe words, <hi>the moſt of the Synod were obedient to what he had diſcourſed; and embraced both mutual Concord, and ſound Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And accordingly S. <hi>Hilary</hi> a little after extols his Son
<hi>Conſtantius</hi> for this, that he adhered to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and blames him onely for not attending to the true Catholick ſenſe of them. His words are theſe, (in his little Book, which he delivered to <hi>Conſtantius) I truly admire thee, O Lord Conſtantius the Emperour, who deſireſt a Faith according to what is written.</hi> They pretended to no other in thoſe days; but, (as he ſpeaks a little after) look'd upon him <hi>that refuſed this, as Antichriſt.</hi> It was onely required that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Faith out of <hi>God's Books,</hi> not merely accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>words</hi> of them, but according to their true <hi>meaning</hi> (becauſe many
<hi>ſpake Scripture without Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and pretended to Faith without Faith,</hi> as his words are) and herein Catholick and conſtant Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63802:11"/>was to guide them. For whatſoever was contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to what the whole Church had received and held from the beginning, could not in reaſon be thought to be the meaning of that Scripture, which was alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to prove it. And, on the other ſide, the Church pretended to no more than to be a Witneſs of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſenſe of the Scriptures: which were the bottom upon which they built this Faith.</p>
            <p>Thus I obſerve <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> ſaith (in
<hi>Euſeb.</hi> his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>L.</hi> IV. <hi>C.</hi> 22.) that when he was at <hi>Rome</hi> he met with a great many Biſhops, and that he
<hi>received the very ſame Doctrine from them all.</hi> And then, a little after, tells us what that was, and whence they derived it, ſaying, <hi>that in every ſucceſſion of Biſhops, and in every City, ſo they held; as the Law preached, and as the Prophets, and as the Lord.</hi> That is, according to the Doctrine of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this particular, with a pregnant paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, which I remember in a famous Divine of our Church (D. <hi>Jackſon,</hi> in his Treatiſe of the Catholick Church, <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.) who writes to this effect,</p>
            <p>That Tradition, which was of ſo much uſe in the Primitive Church, was not <hi>unwritten Traditions</hi> or cuſtoms, commended or ratified by the ſuppoſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falliblity of any viſible Church, but did eſpecially conſiſt in the <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> or
<hi>Regiſters</hi> of particular Churches. And the unanimous conſent of ſo many ſeveral Churches, as exhibited their confeſſions to the
<hi>Nicene</hi> Council, out of ſuch Forms as had been fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and taught before this Controverſie aroſe, about the Divinity of Chriſt; and that voluntarily and freely (theſe Churches being not dependent one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nor overſwayed by any Authority over them; nor miſled by faction to frame their confeſſions of Faith by imitation, or according to ſome pattern ſet them) <pb n="21" facs="tcp:63802:11"/>was a pregnant argument, that this Faith wherein they all agreed, had been delivered to them by the Apoſtles and their followers, and was the true meaning of the holy Writings, in this great Article: and evidently proved, that <hi>Arius</hi> did obtrude ſuch interpretations of Scripture, as had not been heard of before; or were but the ſenſe of ſome private perſons in the Church, and not of the generality of Believers.</p>
            <p>In ſhort the unanimous conſent of ſo many diſtinct viſible Churches, as exhibited their ſeveral Confeſſions, Catechiſms, or Teſtimonies, of their own or Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Faith unto the Council of
<hi>Nice,</hi> was an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame force and efficacy againſt
<hi>Arius</hi> and his partakers, as the General conſent and practice of all Nations, in worſhipping a Divine Power in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, is againſt
<hi>Atheiſts.</hi> Nothing but the ingrafted notion of a Deity, could have induced ſo many ſeveral Nations, ſo much different in natural diſpoſition, in civil diſcipline and education, to affect or practiſe the duty of Adoration. And nothing but the evidence of <hi>the ingrafted word</hi> (as Saint <hi>James</hi> calls the Goſpel) delivered by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, could have kept ſo many ſeveral Churches, as communicated their Confeſſions unto that Council, in the unity of the ſame Faith.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of the reſt of the <hi>four firſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils;</hi> whoſe Decrees are a great confirmation of our belief: becauſe they deliver to us, the conſent of the Churches of Chriſt, in thoſe great Truths, which they aſſert out of the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And could there any <hi>Traditive</hi> Interpretation of the whole Scripture be produced, upon the Authority of ſuch <hi>Original Tradition,</hi> as that now named; we would moſt thankfully and joyfully receive it. But there never was any ſuch pretended; no, not by the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63802:12"/>Roman Church: whoſe Doctours differ among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, about the meaning of hundreds of places in the Bible. Which they would not doe ſure, nor ſpend their time unprofitably, in making the beſt conjectures they are able; if they knew of any expoſition of thoſe places, in which all Chriſtian Doctours had agreed from the beginning.</p>
            <p n="5">V. But more than this, we allow that <hi>Tradition</hi> gives us a conſiderable aſſiſtance, in ſuch points as are not in ſo many letters and ſyllables contained in the Scriptures, but may be gathered from thence, by good and manifeſt reaſoning. Or, in plainer words perhaps, whatſoever <hi>Tradition</hi> juſtifies any Doctrine, that may be proved by the Scriptures, though not found in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs terms there, we acknowledge to be of great uſe, and readily receive and follow it: as ſerving very much to eſtabliſh us more firmly in that Truth, when we ſee all Chriſtians have adhered to it.</p>
            <p>This may be called a <hi>confirming Tradition:</hi> of which we have an inſtance in the Doctrine of <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi> which ſome ancient Fathers call an <hi>Apoſtolical Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Not, that it cannot be proved by any place of Scripture; no ſuch matter: for though we do not find it written in ſo many words that Infants are to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, or that the Apoſtles baptiſed Infants; yet it may be proved out of the Scriptures, and the Fathers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves who call it an <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition</hi> do alledge teſtimonies of the Scriptures to make it good. And therefore we may be ſure, they comprehend the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures within the name of
<hi>Apoſtolical Tradition:</hi> and believed that this Doctrine was gathered out of the Scriptures, though not expreſly treated of there.</p>
            <p>In like manner we, in this Church, aſſert the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Biſhops above Presbyters, by a Divine right: <pb n="23" facs="tcp:63802:12"/>as appears by the Book of Conſecration of Biſhops, where the perſon to be ordained to this Office, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his belief, <hi>that he is truly called to this Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the will of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now this we are perſuaded may be plainly enough proved to any man that is ingenuous and will fairly conſider things, out of the holy
<hi>Scriptures</hi> without the help of <hi>Tradition:</hi> but we alſo take in the aſſiſtance of this for the conviction of gain-ſayers; and by the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al practice and Tradition of the Church from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning confirm our Scripture proofs ſo ſtrongly, that he ſeems to us very obſtinate, or extremely prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that yields not to them. And therefore to make our Doctrine in this point the more Authentick, our Church hath put both theſe proofs together; in the Preface to <hi>the Form of giving Orders:</hi> which begins in theſe words; <hi>It is evident unto all men diligently rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding holy Scripture and ancient Authours, that from the Apoſtles time there have been three Orders of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in Chriſt's Church, Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope no body among us is ſo weak, as to imagine, when he reads this, that by admitting <hi>Tradition</hi> to be of ſuch uſe and force as I have mentioned, we yield too much to the Popiſh Cauſe; which ſupports it ſelf by this pretence. But if any one ſhall ſuggeſt this to any of our people, let them reply; that it is but the pretence, and onely by the Name of
<hi>Tradition,</hi> that the Romiſh Church ſupports it ſelf: For <hi>true Tradition</hi> is as great a proof againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> as it is for
<hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> The very foundation of the Pope's Empire (which is, his ſucceſſion in Saint <hi>Peter</hi>'s Supremacy) is utterly ſubverted by this: the conſtant Tradition of the Church being evidently againſt it. And therefore let us not loſe this Advantage we have againſt them, by ignorantly refuſing to receive true and conſtant <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63802:13"/>which will be ſo far from leading us into their Church; that it will never ſuffer us to think of being of it, while it remains ſo oppoſite to that which is truly Apoſtolical.</p>
            <p>I conclude this, with the direction, which our Church gives to Preachers in the Book of <hi>Canons</hi> 1571. (in the Title
<hi>Concionatores</hi>) that <hi>no man ſhall teach the people any thing to be held and believed by them religiouſly, but what is conſentaneous to the Doctrine of the Old and New Teſtament; and what the Catholick Fathers and ancient Biſhops, have gathered out of that very Doctrine.</hi> This is our Rule, whereby we are to guide our ſelves: which was ſet us on purpoſe, to preſerve our Preachers from broaching any idle, novel, or popiſh Doctrines; as appears by the Concluſion of that Injunction, <hi>Vain, and old Wives opinions, and hereſies, and popiſh errours, abhorring from the Doctrine and Faith of Chriſt, they ſhall not teach: nor any thing at all whereby the unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full multitude, may be inflamed either to the ſtudy of novelty, or to contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. But though nothing may be taught as a piece of Religion, which hath not the forenamed Original; yet I muſt add that thoſe things, which have been univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally believed, and not contrary to Scripture, though not written at all there, nor to be proved from thence, we do receive as pious opinions. For inſtance, the <hi>perpetual Virginity</hi> of the Mother of God our Saviour: which is ſo likely a thing, and ſo univerſally received; that I do not ſee why we ſhould not look upon it, as a genuine
<hi>Apoſtolical Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. I have but one thing more to add, which is, that we allow alſo the <hi>Traditions</hi> of the Church, about matters of <hi>Order, Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> Onely we <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63802:13"/>do not take them to be parts of God's Worſhip; and if they be not appointed in the holy Scriptures, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they may be altered by the ſame or the like au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, with that which ordained them. So our Church hath excellently and fully reſolved us, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch matters, in the <hi>XXXIV.</hi> Article of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: where there are <hi>three</hi> things aſſerted concerning ſuch <hi>Traditions</hi> as theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>It is not neceſſary that Traditions and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> (they are the very firſt words of the Article) <hi>be in all places, one or utterly alike: for at all times they have been divers, and may be changed according to the diverſities of Countries, times, and mens manners, ſo that nothing be ordained againſt God's word.</hi> But then to prevent all diſorders and confuſions, that men might make in the Church, by following their own private fancies and humours; the next thing which is decreed is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> that <hi>whoſoever through his own private judgment, willingly and purpoſely doth openly break the Traditions and Ceremonies of the Church, which be not repugnant to the word of God, and be ordained and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by common authority; ought to be rebuked openly (that others may fear to doe the like) as he that offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth againſt the common order of the Church, and hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Authority of the Magiſtrate, and woundeth the Conſciences of the weak Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> it is there declared, that <hi>every particular or national Church, hath authority to ordain, change and aboliſh, Ceremonies or Rites of the Church, ordained onely by man's authority, ſo that all things be done to edifying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is ſufficient to ſhew what we believe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<hi>Traditions,</hi> about matters of Order and Decency.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63802:14"/>
            <p n="8">VIII. As for what is delivered in matters of Doctrine, or Order, by any private Doctour in the Church, or by any particular Church, it appears by what hath been ſaid, that it cannot be taken to be more than the private opinion of that man, or the particular decree of that Church; and can have no more authority than they have: that is, cannot oblige all Chriſtians, unleſs it be conteined in the holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>Now ſuch are the Traditions which the Roman Church would impoſe upon us; and impoſe upon us after a ſtrange faſhion, as you ſhall ſee in the <hi>Second Part</hi> of this Diſcourſe: unto which I ſhall proceed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, when I have left with you this brief reflexion on what hath been ſaid in this <hi>Firſt Part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our people may hereby be admoniſhed not to ſuffer themſelves to be deceived and abuſed by words and empty names, without their ſenſe and meaning. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more common than this: eſpecially in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Traditions.</hi> About which a great ſtir is raiſed; and it is commonly given out, that we refuſe all Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Than which nothing is more falſe: for we refuſe none truly ſo called; that is Doctrines delivered by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles. No, we refuſe nothing at all, becauſe it is unwritten: but merely becauſe we are not ſure, it is delivered by that Authority, towhich we ought to ſubmit.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever is delivered to us by our Lord and his Apoſtles, we receive as the very word of God: which we think is ſufficiently declared in the holy Scriptures. But if any can certainly prove, by any Authority equal to that which brings the Scriptures to us, that there is any thing elſe delivered by them, we receive that alſo. The Controverſie will ſoon be at an end: for we are ready to embrace it, when any ſuch thing can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:63802:14"/>
            <p>Nay, we have that reverence for thoſe who ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Apoſtles, that what they have unanimouſly delivered to us, as the ſenſe of any doubtfull place, we receive it, and ſeek no farther. There is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, whether or no we ſhould entertain it.</p>
            <p>To the Decrees of the Church alſo we ſubmit in matters of Decency and Order: yea, and acquieſce in its authority, when it determines doubtfull opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>But we cannot receive that as a Doctrine of Chriſt, which we know is but the Tradition of man: nor keep the Ordinances of the ancient Church in matters of Decency, ſo unalterably as never to vary from them; becauſe they themſelves did not intend them to be of everlaſting obligation. As appears by the changes that have been made in ſeveral times and places: even in ſome things which are mentioned in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; being but cuſtomes ſuted to thoſe Ages and Countries.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, <hi>Traditions</hi> we do receive; but not all that are called by that name. Thoſe which have ſufficient Authority; but not thoſe which are impoſed upon us, by the ſole authority of one particular Church, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a power over all the reſt. And ſo I come to the Second Part.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63802:15"/>
            <head>PART II. <hi>What</hi> Traditions <hi>we do not receive.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. AND in the firſt place we do not believe that there is any <hi>Tradition,</hi> which contains <hi>another word of God:</hi> which is not in the Scripture, or cannot be proved from thence. In this conſiſts the main dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between us, and them of the Romiſh perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: who affirm that Divine Truth which we are all bound to receive, to be partly written; partly delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by word of mouth without writing. Which is not onely the affirmation of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in more expreſs terms, in the Preface to the <hi>Roman Catechiſm,</hi> drawn up by their order: where we find theſe words (towards the concluſion of it)
<hi>the whole Doctrine to be delivered to the faithfull, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the word of God: which</hi> (word of God) <hi>is diſtributed into Scripture, and Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a full and plain declaration of their mind; with which we can by no means agree, for divers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not onely becauſe the Scriptures teſtifie to their own perfection; which they affirm to be ſo great, as to be able to complete the divineſt men in the Church of Chriſt, in all points of heavenly wiſedom, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> III. 15, 16, 17. but</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe the conſtant Tradition of the Church (even of the Roman Church anciently) is, that <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63802:15"/>in the Scriptures we may find all that is neceſſary to be known and believed to Salvation. I muſt not fill up this Paper, with Authorities to this purpoſe: but we avow this, unto the people of our Church, for a certain Truth, which hath been demonſtrated by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Writers: who have ſhewn that the ancient Doctours univerſally, ſpeak the language of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> IV. 7. <hi>not to think above that which is written.</hi> I will mention onely theſe memorable words of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> who is as earneſt an Advocate as any for ritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Traditions, but having to deal with
<hi>Hermogenes</hi> in a queſtion of Faith, <hi>whether all things in the beginning were made of nothing,</hi> urges him in this manner. I have no where yet read, that all things were made out of a ſubject matter. <hi>If it be written, let thoſe of Hermogenes his ſhop ſhew it; if it be not written, let them fear that woe which is allotted to ſuch, as add or take away.</hi> The very ſame anſwer ſhould our people make to thoſe, that would have them receive any thing as an Article of Faith, which is not delivered to them by this truly Apoſtolical Church wherein we live. <hi>If it be written, let us ſee it; if it be not, take heed how you add to the undoubted word of God.</hi> We receive the holy Scriptures, as able to make us wiſe to Salvation. So they themſelves tell us; and ſo runs the True Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Church: which you of the Romiſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion have forſaken; but we adhere unto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And we have this farther reaſon ſo to doe, becauſe if part of God's word had been written, and part un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, we cannot but believe there would have been ſome care taken, in the written Word, not onely to let us know ſo much; but alſo inform us whither we ſhould reſort to find it, and how we ſhould know it; if it be abſolutely neceſſary for us to be acquainted with it. But there is no ſuch notice, nor any ſuch
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63802:16"/>directions left us; nor can any man give us any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rule to follow in this matter, but onely this: <hi>to examine all Traditions by the Scripture, as the ſupreme Rule of Faith; and to admit onely ſuch, as are confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. For which we have ſtill this farther reaſon, that no ſooner were they that firſt delivered and received the holy Scriptures gone out of the world, but we find men began to add their own fancies unto the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Truth: which made it abſolutely neceſſary to keep to the Tradition in the holy Scriptures; all other growing uncertain. This is obſerved by <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> himſelf (in <hi>Euſebius L. III. C.</hi> 32.) that <hi>the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained a chaſt Virgin, and the Spouſe of Chriſt, till the ſacred Quire of the Apoſtles, and the next generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, who had had the honour to be their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, were extinct: and then there began a plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of impious, atheiſtical errour; by the fraud of teachers, who delivered other doctrine.</hi> Which was a thing Saint <hi>Paul</hi> feared even in his own life-time, about the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> XI. 3.) leſt, the Devil, like a wily Serpent, ſhould beguile them, and corrupt their minds, from the original ſimplicity of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine wherein they were firſt inſtructed. And if it were attempted then; it was leſs difficult, and therefore more endeavoured afterward: as ſhall appear anon by plain Hiſtory; which tells how ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons pretended they received, this and that from an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. Some of which Traditions were preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; others received, and afterwards found to be impoſtures. Which ſhews there was ſo much falſe dealing in the caſe, that it was hard for men to know what was truly Apoſtolical in thoſe days, if it came to them this way onely; and therefore impoſſible to be diſcerned by us now, at this great diſtance of time <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63802:16"/>from the Apoſtles: who we know delivered the true Faith; but we have no reaſon to rely upon mere Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, without Scripture, for any part of that Faith; when we ſee what cheats were put upon men by that means, even then when they had better helps to detect them than we have.</p>
            <p>It is true, the Fathers ſometime urge <hi>Tradition</hi> as a proof of what they ſay. But we muſt know, that the Scriptures were not preſently communicated, among ſome Barbarous Nations; and there were ſome Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks alſo who either denied the Scriptures, or ſome part of them: and in theſe caſes it was neceſſary, to appeal to the Tradition that was in the Church; and to convince them by the Doctrine taught every where by all the Biſhops. But that (mark this, I pray you) of which they convinced them by this argument, was nothing but what is taught in the Scripture.</p>
            <p n="5">5. With which we cannot ſuffer any thing to be equalled in authority; unleſs we would ſee it confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the ſame or equal Teſtimony. This is the great reaſon of all, why we cannot admit any unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Traditions to be a part of the word of God, which we are bound to believe; becauſe we cannot find any truths ſo delivered to us, as thoſe in the holy Scriptures. They come to us with as full a teſtimony as can be deſired, of their Divine Original: but ſo do none of thoſe things, which are now obtruded on us by the Romiſh Church under the name of
<hi>Traditions</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written word</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>For the primitive Church had the very firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, and authentick Writings, of thoſe Books, called the New Teſtament, delivered by the Apoſtles own hands to them. And thoſe Books confirm the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Old Teſtament: and they were both deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to poſterity, by that primitive Church; witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63802:17"/>from whom they received them: who carefully kept them as the moſt pretious Treaſure; ſo that this written word hath had the general approbation, and teſtimony of the whole Church of Chriſt in every age, untill this day; witneſſing that it is Divine. And it hath been the conſtant buſineſs of the Doctours of the Church, to expound this word of God to the people: and their Books are full of citations out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; all agreeing, in ſubſtance, with what we now reade in them. Nay, the very enemies of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſuch as
<hi>Celſus, Porphyry, Julian</hi> never queſtioned, but theſe are the writings of which the Apoſtles were the Authours, and which they delivered. Beſides, the Marks they have in themſelves, of a Divine Spirit, which indited them: they all tending to breed and preſerve in men a ſenſe of God, and to make them truly vertuous.</p>
            <p>Not one word of which can be ſaid for any of thoſe
<hi>unwritten Traditions,</hi> which the Roman Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be a part of God's word. For we have no te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of them in the holy Scriptures. Nor doth the primitive Church affirm ſhe received them from the Apoſtles, as ſhe did the written word. Nor have they the perpetual conſent and general approbation of the whole Church ever ſince. Nor are they frequently quoted, as the words of Scripture are upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, by the Doctours of the Church. Nor do we find them to be the Doctrine, which was conſtantly taught the people. Nor is there any notice taken of them by the enemies of our Faith; whoſe aſſaults are all againſt the Scriptures. In ſhort, they are ſo far from having any true authority; that counterfeit teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and forged writings have been their great ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters. Beſides the plain drift of them, which is not to make all men better, but to make ſome richer:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63802:17"/>and the manifeſt danger men are in, by many of them, to be drawn away from God, to put their truſt and confidence in Creatures. As might be ſhewn, if this Paper would contain it, in their Doctrines, of
<hi>Papal Supremacy, Purgatory, Invocation of Saints, Image Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and divers others.</p>
            <p>Concerning which we ſay, as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> doth to
<hi>Pompeius,</hi> about another matter. <hi>If it be commanded in the Goſpels, or in the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, or in their Acts, that they ſhould not be baptiſed who return from any Hereſie, but onely be received by impoſition of hands, LET THIS DIVINE and HOLT TRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DITION BE OBSERVED.</hi> The ſame ſay we, if there be any thing in the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> in the
<hi>Epiſtles,</hi> in the <hi>Acts,</hi> concerning Invocations of Saints, concerning the praying Souls out of Purgatory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, that holy Tradition be obſerved. But if it be not there, <hi>what obſtinacy is this</hi> (as it follows a little after in that Epiſt.
<hi>LXXIV.</hi>) <hi>what preſumption, to prefer humane Tradition, before the Divine diſpoſition or ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A great deal more there is in that place, and in others of that holy Martyr, to bring all to the <hi>ſource, the root, the original of the Divine Tradition; for then humane errour ceaſes:</hi> which original Tradition he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms to be, what is delivered in the holy Scriptures: which delivering to us the whole will of God concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning us, we look after no other Tradition, but what explains, and confirms, and is conſonant to this. For we believe that what is delivered to us by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and what is delivered by true Tradition, are but two ſeveral ways of bringing us acquainted with the ſame Chriſtian Truth; not with different parts of that Truth.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63802:18"/>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the firſt thing; the ſum of which is this. We do not receive any Tradition, or Doctrine to ſupply the defect of the Scripture, in ſome neceſſary Article of Faith: which Doctrines, they of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend to have one and the ſame Authour with the Scripture,
<hi>viz.</hi> God; and therefore to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with the ſame pious affection and reverence: but cannot tell us where we may find them, how we ſhall diſcern true from falſe, nor give us any aſſurance of their Truth, but we muſt take them purely upon their word.</p>
            <q>Now how little reaſon we have to truſt to that, will appear in the <hi>ſecond</hi> thing I have to add: which is this,</q>
            <p n="2">II. That we dare not receive any thing whatſoever merely upon the Credit of the Roman Church: no not <hi>that divine, that holy Tradition</hi> before ſpoken of, <hi>viz.</hi> the Scripture. Which we do not believe onely upon their teſtimony; both becauſe they are but a part of the Church and therefore not the ſole keepers of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truth; and they are a corrupted part who have not approved themſelves faithfull in the keeping what was committed to them.</p>
            <p>Let our people diligently mark this, that Traditions never were, nor are now, onely in the keeping of the Roman Church: and that theſe things are widely dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent; the Tradition of the whole Church, or of the greateſt and beſt part of it; and the Tradition of one part of the Church, and the leaſt part of it; and the worſt part alſo and moſt depraved.</p>
            <p>What is warranted by the Authority of the whole Church, I have ſhewn before, we reverently receive: but we cannot take that for current Tradition, which <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63802:18"/>is warranted onely by a ſmall part of the Church, and we give very little credit to what is warranted onely by that part of it which is <hi>Roman.</hi> Becauſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> This Church hath not preſerved ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as other Churches have done, the <hi>firſt and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Tradition,</hi> which is in the Scriptures: but ſuffered them to be ſhamefully corrupted. Every one knows that there is a <hi>Latine Vulgar</hi> Edition of the Bible (which they of that Church prefer before the Original) none of which they preſerved heretofore from mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt depravations; nor have been able, ſince they were told of the faults, to purge away; ſo as to canonize any Edition without permitting great numbers in their neweſt and moſt approved Bibles. <hi>Iſidore Clarius</hi> in his Preface to his Edition, complains that he found theſe holy Writings defaced with innumerable errours: <hi>Eight thouſand</hi> of which, that he thought moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, he ſaith he amended; and yet left he knew not how many leſſer ones untouched: After which (the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> having vouched this Vulgar Latine Edition, for the onely authentick) Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the
<hi>Fifth,</hi> publiſhed, out of the ſeveral Copies that were abroad, one which he ſtraitly charged to be received, as the onely true Vulgar; from which none ſhould dare to vary in a tittle. And yet two years were ſcarce paſſed, before <hi>Clemens</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> found many defects and corruptions ſtill remaining in that Edition: and therefore publiſhed another, with the very ſame charge, that none elſe ſhould be received.</p>
            <p>Which evidently ſhews they have ſuffered the holy Books to be ſo fouly abuſed, that they know not how to amend the errours that are crept into them; nor can tell which is the true Bible. For theſe two Bibles thus equally authoriſed, as the onely authentick ones, abound not onely with manifeſt diverſities; but with <pb n="36" facs="tcp:63802:19"/>contradictions, or contrarieties, one to the other. Whereby all Romaniſts are reduced to this miſerable neceſſity, either to make uſe of no Bible at all; or to fall under the curſe of <hi>Sixtus</hi> if he make uſe the Bible of
<hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> or the curſe of <hi>Clement,</hi> if he uſe the Bible of
<hi>Sixtus.</hi> For they are both of them enjoined, with the excluſion of all other Editions; and with the penalty of a curſe upon them, who diſobey the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and it is impoſſible to obey both.</p>
            <p>This might be ſufficient to demonſtrate how unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that Church hath been, in the weightieſt concerns. Whereby all the members of it are plunged, beyond all power of redemption, into a diſmal neceſſity, either of laving aſide the Scriptures; or of offending againſt the ſacred decrees (as they account them) of one or other of the heads of their Church (which ſome take to be infallible) and being accurſed of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But for every one's fuller ſatisfaction, it may be fit farther to repreſent, how negligent they have been in preſerving other Traditions, which were certainly once in the Church, but now utterly loſt. There is no queſtion to be made, but the Apoſtles taught the firſt Chriſtians, the meaning of thoſe hard places which we find in their, and other holy, Writings. But who can tell us where to find certainly ſo much as one of them? and therefore where is the fidelity of this Church, which boaſts ſo much to be the keeper of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Traditions? For nothing is more deſirable than thoſe Apoſtolical interpretations of Scripture; nothing could be more uſefull; and yet we have no hope to meet with them either there, or indeed any where elſe. Which is no reproach to other Churches, who do not pretend to more than is written; but reflects much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and diſcredits them, who challenge the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the whole Church intirely, and would paſs not <pb n="37" facs="tcp:63802:19"/>onely for the ſole keepers and witneſſes of Divine Truth; but for carefull preſervers of it. For of what ſhould they have been more carefull than of theſe uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things; whereof they can tell us nothing? when of unprofitable Ceremonies they have moſt devoutly kept, if we could believe them, a very great number.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They tell us indeed of ſome doctrinal Traditions alſo which they have religiouſly preſerved: but mark I beſeech you with what ſincerity. For to juſtifie theſe, they have forged great numbers of Writings, and Books under the name of ſuch Authours, as it is evident had no hand in them: which is another reaſon why we cannot give credit to their reports, if we have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther authority. There are very ſew perſons now that are ignorant how many <hi>Decretal Epiſtles</hi> of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> have been deviſed, to eſtabliſh the Papal Empire: and how ſhamefully a Donation of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> hath been pretended, wherein he gave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Roman Empire and all its rights to the Pope. Which puts me in mind (as a notorious proof of this) of the forgeries that are in the <hi>Breviary</hi> it ſelf: where we reade of
<hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Leproſie, and the cure of it by
<hi>Sylveſter</hi>'s baptizing him (which are egregious Fables) and of the Decrees of the ſecond Roman Synod under that Pope <hi>Sylveſter;</hi> wherein the <hi>Breviary</hi> affirms <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> was condemned: when all the world knows, that <hi>Photinus</hi> his Hereſie did not ſpring up till divers years after the death of <hi>Sylveſter.</hi> And there are ſo many other arguments which prove the Decrees of that <hi>Synod</hi> to be a vile forgery, that we may ſee, by the way, what reaſon they have to keep their Liturgy in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Language: leſt the people perceiving what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths they are taught, inſtead of God's word, ſhould abhor that Divine Service, as juſtly they might, which is ſtuffed with ſo many Fables.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:63802:20"/>
            <p>It would be endleſs to ſhew how many paſſages they have foiſted into ancient Writers to countenance their Traditions; particularly about the Papal Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy: by which ſo great a man as <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> was deceived: who frequently quotes authorities, which are mere forgeries; though not invented by him, I verily think, but impoſed upon him by the fraud which had been long practiſed in that Church. For we find that the Canons of ſo famous and univerſally known <hi>Council</hi> as that of the firſt at <hi>Nice,</hi> have been falſely alledged even by Popes themſelves. <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> for inſtance, and <hi>Zoſimus</hi> alledged a counterfeit <hi>Nicene</hi> Canon to the African Biſhops in the Sixth Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Carthage:</hi> who to convince the falſe dealing of theſe Popes ſought out with great labour and diligence, the ancient and authentick Copies of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons; and having obtained them both from <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> and from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> they found them for number and for ſenſe to be the very ſame, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves already had; but not one word in them, of what the <hi>Popes</hi> pretended. The ſame I might ſay of Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> and others; whom I purpoſely omit, becauſe I ſtudy brevity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And have this farther to add, that as they have pretended
<hi>Tradition</hi> where there is none; ſo where there is, they have left that <hi>Tradition:</hi> and therefore have no reaſon to expect that we ſhould be governed by them in this matter; who take the liberty to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, as they pleaſe, better Tradition than they would impoſe upon us. None are to be charged, with this, if it be a guilt, more than themſelves. For inſtance the <hi>three immerſions:</hi> i.e. dipping the perſons three times in Baptiſm, was certainly an ancient practice; and ſaid by many Authours to be an Apoſtolical Tradition; and to be ordained in ſignification of the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <pb n="39" facs="tcp:63802:20"/>into whoſe name they were baptiſed. And yet there is no ſuch thing now in uſe, in their Church; no more than in ours: who juſtifie our ſelves, as I ſhewed above, by a true opinion, that Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies are not unalterable: which it is impoſſible for them to do, unleſs they will ceaſe to preſs the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of other Traditions upon us, which never were ſo generally received, as this which is now aboliſhed. To which may be added the cuſtome of giving the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt to Infants;</hi> which prevailed for ſeveral Ages; and is called by S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> an <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition:</hi> the cuſtome of adminiſtring Baptiſm onely at
<hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide;</hi> with a great heap more, which it would be too long to enumerate. Nor is it neceſſary I ſhould trouble the Reader with them; theſe being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſhew, the partiality of that Church in this matter: and that we have no reaſon to be tied to that, merely upon their Authority; which they will not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, though having a far greater. Nay, all diſcreet perſons may eaſily ſee, what a wide difference there is, between them who have abrogated ſuch Traditions, as had long gone even in their Church, under the name of Apoſtolical; and us who therefore do not follow pretended Traditions now, becauſe we believe them not to be <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> but merely <hi>Roman.</hi> He is ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blind, who doth not ſee how much more ſincere this Church is, than that; in this regard.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Beſides this, we can demonſtrate, that as in theſe things they have forſaken Traditions, ſo in other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they have perverted and abuſed them; turning them into quite another thing. As appears to all that underſtand any thing of ancient learning, in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of
<hi>Purgatory:</hi> which none of the moſt ancient Writers ſo much as dreamt to be ſuch a place, as they have now deviſed: but onely aſſerted a <hi>Purgatory Fire,</hi> 
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:63802:21"/>through which all, both good and bad, even the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin her ſelf, muſt paſs; at the great and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day of Judgment. This was the old <hi>Tradition,</hi> as we may call it, which was among Chriſtians: which they have changed into ſuch a
<hi>Tradition</hi> as was among the Pagans.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But it is time to have done with this: elſe I ſhould have inſiſted upon this a while, which I touched before and is of great moment: that <hi>the Tradition which now runs in that Church is contrary to the certain Tradition of the Apoſtles and the univerſal Church:</hi> particularly in the <hi>Canon of Scripture.</hi> In which no more Books have been numbred by the Catholick Church in all Ages, ſince the Apoſtles time, than are in the VI. Article of Religion in this Church of <hi>England:</hi> till the late Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> took the boldneſs to thruſt the
<hi>Apocryphal Books</hi> into the holy Canon; as nothing inferiour to the acknowledged Divine Writings. This hath been ſo evidently demonſtrated by a late Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Prelate of our Church, in his <hi>Scholaſtical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Canon of the Scriptures,</hi> out of undoubted Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords; that no fair Anſwer can be made to it.</p>
            <p>But I muſt leave a little room for other things that ought to be noted.</p>
            <p n="3">III. And the next is a conſequence from what hath been now ſaid. That there being ſo little credit to be given to the Roman Church onely, we cannot receive thoſe Doctrines for Truth, which that Church now preſſes upon our belief, upon the account of <hi>Tradition.</hi> For inſtance, that <hi>the Church of Rome, is the Mother and Miſtreſs of all other Churches;</hi> that <hi>the Pope of Rome is the Monarch or Head of the univerſal viſible Church;</hi> that <hi>all Scriptures muſt be expounded according to the ſenſe of this Church;</hi> that <hi>there are truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <pb n="41" facs="tcp:63802:21"/>ſeven Sacraments, neither more nor leſs, inſtituted by our bleſſed Lord himſelf in the New Teſtament;</hi> that <hi>there is a proper and propitiatory Sacrifice offered in the Maſs for the quick and dead, the ſame that Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered on the Croſs;</hi> in ſhort, the <hi>half Communion,</hi> and all the reſt of the Articles of their New Faith, in the Creed publiſhed by <hi>Pope Pius</hi> IV. which are Traditions of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church alone, not of the
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal:</hi> and rely ſolely upon their own Authority. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we refuſe them; and in our diſputes about <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> we mean theſe things; which we reject becauſe they have no foundation, either in the holy Scripture, or in Univerſal Tradition: but depend, as I ſaid, upon the ſole Authority of that Church, which witneſſes in its own behalf.</p>
            <p>For whatſoever is pretended, to make the better ſhew, all reſolves at laſt into that; as I intimated in the beginning of this Diſcourſe. <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> can doe nothing at all for them; without their <hi>Churches definition.</hi> Though their whole infallible Rule of Faith ſeem to be made up of thoſe <hi>three,</hi> yet in truth, the laſt of theſe alone, the <hi>Churches definition,</hi> is the whole Rule; and the very bottom upon which their Faith ſtands. For what is Tradition is no more apparent, than, what is Scripture, according to their principles, without the Authority of their Church: which pretends to an unlimited power to ſupply the defect even of <hi>Tradition</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, as Tradition among them is taken in to ſupply the defect of Scripture; ſo the Authority of their Church is taken in to ſupply the defect of Tradition: but this Authority undermines them both; becauſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture nor Tradition ſignifie any thing, without their Churches Authority. Which therefore, is the rule of their Faith: that is, they believe themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:63802:22"/>
            <p>To which abſurdity they are driven; becauſe it is made evident by us that there have been great diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Traditions, and many changes and alterations made, even in things called Apoſtolical, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have no other way, but to fly to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the preſent Roman Church, to determine what are Traditions Apoſtolical, and what are not: by which judgment all mankind muſt be governed; that is, we muſt believe them; and they believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: which they would have done well to have ſaid in one word; without putting us to the trouble of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for Traditions in Books, and in other Churches. But they would willingly colour their pretences, by as many fair words, as is poſſible, and ſo make mention of <hi>Scripture, Tradition, Antiquity:</hi> which when we have examined, they will not ſtand to them; but take fanctuary in their own Authority: ſaying they are the ſole judges what is Scripture, and what Tradition, and what Antiquity; nay have a power to declare any new point of Faith, which the Church never heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This is the Doctrine of
<hi>Salmeron</hi> and others of his fellows; that <hi>the Doctrine of Faith admits of addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in eſſential things. For all things were not taught by the Apoſtles, but ſuch as were then neceſſary and fit for the Salvation of Believers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which means we can never know, when the Chriſtian Religion will be perfected: but their Church may bring in <hi>Traditions</hi> by its ſole Authority, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſome among them have been contented to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve all their Faith into the ſole Authority of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Roman Biſhop: according to that famous ſaying of <hi>Cornelius Muſſus</hi> (promoted by
<hi>Paul</hi> III. to a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick) upon the <hi>XIV.</hi> Chapter to the
<hi>Romans; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the truth ingenuouſly, I would give greater credit to <pb n="43" facs="tcp:63802:22"/>one Pope, in thoſe things which touch the myſteries of Faith; than to a thouſand Hierom's, Auſtin's, Gregory's: to ſay nothing of Richard's, Scotus's,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for I believe and know that the Pope cannot err in matters of Faith.</hi> Which contemptuous ſpeech he would never have ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, to the diſcredit of thoſe great men whom they pretend to reverence; if he had not known more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that the Tradition which runs among the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers, is againſt them; than he could know the Pope to be infallible.</p>
            <p>There is no Tradition, I am ſure for that; nor for abundance of other things, which reſt merely upon their own credit; as is fairly acknowledged in two great Articles of their preſent Creed by our Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Biſhop <hi>Fiſher</hi> with whoſe words I conclude this particular.
<hi>Many perhaps have the leſs confidence in Indulgences becauſe their uſe ſeems to have been newer in the Church, and very lately found among Chriſtians. To whom I anſwer, that it doth not appear certainly by whom they began to be firſt delivered. For the ancients make no mention, or very rare of Purgatory: and the Greeks to this very day do not believe it: nor was the belief either of Purgatory or of Indulgences, ſo neceſſary in the Primitive Church, as it is now. And as long as there was no care about Purgatory, no body ſought for Indulgences: for all their eſteem depends upon that. If you take away Purgatory to what purpoſe are Indulgences? Since therefore Purgatory was ſo lately known and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Catholick Church, who can wonder that there was no uſe of Indulgences in the beginning of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is a full confeſſion what kind of <hi>Traditions</hi> that Church commends unto us: things lately inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; their own private opinions, of which the ancient Chriſtians knew nothing. In one word, their Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <pb n="44" facs="tcp:63802:23"/>is no Tradition; in that ſenſe wherein the Church always underſtood it.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And what hath been ſaid of them, muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to other particular Churches; though ſome have been more ſincere than they. None of them hath any authority to commend any thing as an Article of Faith unto poſterity; which hath not been commended to them by all foregoing Ages, derived from the Apoſtles. For <hi>Vincentius</hi> his Rule is to guide us all in this, <hi>that is Catholick</hi> (and conſequently to be received)
<hi>which hath been held by all, and in all Churches, and at all times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. Which puts me in mind of another thing to be briefly touched; that the Eccleſiaſtical Tradition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Confeſſions or Regiſters of particular Churches in theſe days wherein we live; is not received by us, nor allowed to have the ſame Authority which ſuch Tradition had at the time of the Nicene Council, for the conviction of Hereſie. The joint conſent I mean of ſo many Biſhops as were there aſſembled, and the unanimous Confeſſions of ſo many ſeveral Churches of ſeveral Provinces as were there delivered, hath not now ſuch a force to induce belief, as it had then. The reaſon of which is given by the ſame <hi>Vincentius,</hi> who ſo highly commends that way which was then taken, of reproving Hereſie: but adds this moſt wiſe caution (in the laſt Chapter but one of the firſt Part of his <hi>Commonitorium) but you muſt not think that all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and always are thus to be oppoſed; but onely new and freſh Hereſies: when they firſt riſe up, that is; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have falſified the rules of the ancient Faith,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As for inveterate Hereſies, which have ſpred themſelves, they are in no wiſe to be aſſaulted this way: becauſe in <pb n="45" facs="tcp:63802:23"/>a long tract of time many opportunities may have preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves to Hereticks, of ſtealing Truth, out of ancient Records, and of corrupting the Volumes of our Anceſtours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which if it be applied to the preſent ſtate of things, it is evident the Roman Church hath had ſuch oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of falſifying Antiquity ever ſince the firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the <hi>Papal Supremacy</hi> that we cannot rely merely upon any written teſtimonies, or unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Traditions, which never ſo great a number of their Biſhops met together ſhall produce: which amount not to ſo much as one legal Teſtimony: but they are to be look'd upon or ſuſpected as a multitude of falſe <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> conſpiring together in their own cauſe.</p>
            <p>How then, may ſome ſay, can Hereſies of long ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding be confuted? The ſame <hi>Vincentius</hi> reſolves us in this, in the very next words, <hi>We may convince them, if need be, by the ſole authority of the Scriptures; or eſchew them as already convicted and condemned in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times, by the general Councils of Catholick Prieſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Tradition which is found there, muſt direct all future Councils; not the opinions of their own preſent Churches.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. I will add but one thing more: which is, That the
<hi>Tradition</hi> called <hi>Oral,</hi> becauſe it comes by word of mouth from one Age to another, without any written record, is the moſt uncertain, and can be leaſt relied upon, of all other. This hath been demonſtrated ſo fully by the Writers of our Church, and there are ſuch pregnant inſtances of the errours into which men have been led by it, that it needs no long diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Two inſtances of it are very common, and I ſhall add a third.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63802:24"/>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is that which <hi>Papias,</hi> who lived preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the Apoſtles times, and converſed with thoſe who had ſeen them, ſet on foot. His way was, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates out of his Works, not ſo much to reade, as to inquire of the Elders, what Saint
<hi>Andrew,</hi> or Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid; what was the ſaying of Saint
<hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> Saint <hi>James,</hi> and the reſt of the Diſciples of our Lord. And he pretended that ſome of them told him, among other things, that after the reſurrection of our Bodies, we ſhall reign a thouſand years here upon Earth: which he gathered, ſaith <hi>Euſebius,</hi> from ſome ſaying of the Apoſtles wrong underſtood. But this fancy was embraced very greedily, and was taught for <hi>two</hi> whole Ages, as an
<hi>Apoſtolical Tradition;</hi> no body oppoſing it: and yet having nothing to ſay for it, but onely <hi>the antiquity of the man</hi> (as
<hi>Euſebius</hi> his words are <hi>L.</hi> III. <hi>Cap. ult.</hi>) who delivered it to them: yet this <hi>Tradition</hi> hath been generally ſince taken for an impoſture; and teaches us no more than this; that if one man could ſet a going ſuch a Doctrine, and make it paſs ſo cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent for ſo long a time, upon no other pretence, than that an Apoſtle ſaid ſo in private diſcourſe; we have great reaſon to think that other Traditions have had no better beginning, or not ſo good; eſpecially ſince they never ſo univerſally prevailed as that did.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>ſecond</hi> inſtance is that famous contention about the obſervation of <hi>Eaſter;</hi> which miſerably afflicted the Church in the days of <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> by dividing the Eaſtern Chriſtians from the Weſtern. One pretending Tradition from Saint <hi>John,</hi> and Saint <hi>Philip;</hi> the other from Saint
<hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> Concerning which I will not ſay, as
<hi>Rigaltius</hi> doth (in his ſharp note upon the words of
<hi>Firmilian;</hi> who pretended Tradition for the rebaptizing of Hereticks) that <hi>under the Names and Perſons of great men, there <pb n="47" facs="tcp:63802:24"/>were ſottiſh and ſophiſtical things delivered for Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Traditions, by fools and ſophiſters.</hi> But this I affirm, that there are many more inſtances of mens forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and they neither
<hi>fools</hi> nor <hi>ſophiſters,</hi> but onely wedded to the opinions of their own Churches, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude things as Apoſtolical, for which they had no proof at all. For when they knew not how to defend themſelves, preſently they flew to <hi>Tradition Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A third inſtance of whoſe uncertainty we have in
<hi>Irenaeus</hi> (<hi>L.</hi> II. <hi>C.</hi> 39.) concerning the age of our bleſſed Saviour when he died: which he confidently affirms to have been forty, if not fifty years; and ſaith the Elders which knew Saint
<hi>John</hi> and were his Scholars, received this relation from him. And yet all agree, that he beginning to preach at <hi>thirty</hi> years of age, was crucified about three years and an half after.</p>
            <p>The like relation <hi>Clemens</hi> makes of his preaching but
<hi>one</hi> year; which he calls a ſecret Tradition from the Apoſtles: but hath no more Truth in it, than the other.</p>
            <p>Now if in the firſt Ages, when they were ſo near the fountain and beginning of Tradition men were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, nay ſuch great men as theſe were deceived, and led others into errours in theſe matters: we cannot with any ſafety truſt to Traditions, that have paſſed, men pretend, from one to another untill now: but we can find no mention of in any Writer, till ſome Ages after the Apoſtles; and then were by ſome-body or other, who had authority in thoſe days, called Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Traditions; merely to gain them the more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Thus <hi>Andreas Caeſarienſis</hi> in his Commentaries upon the Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> p. 743. ſaith that the coming of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> before the ſecond coming of Chriſt (though it be not found in Scripture) was a <pb n="48" facs="tcp:63802:25"/>conſtant report received by <hi>Tradition without any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation,</hi> from the teachers of the Church.</p>
            <p>Which is ſufficient to ſhew how ready they were to father their own private opinions, upon ancient univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Tradition: and how little reaſon we have to truſt to that, which was ſo uncertain, even in the firſt Ages; and therefore muſt needs be more dubious now.</p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to lay before the eyes of thoſe, who will be pleaſed to look over this ſhort Treatiſe; what they are to think and ſpeak about <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi> It is a calumny to affirm that the Church of <hi>England</hi> rejects all Tradition; and I hope none of her true Children are ſo ignorant, as when they hear that word to imagine they muſt riſe up and oppoſe it. No, the Scripture it ſelf is a Tradition; and we admit all other Traditions which are ſubordinate, and agreeable unto that; together with all thoſe things which can be proved to be Apoſtolical by the General Teſtimony of the Church in all Ages: nay, if any thing not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Scripture, which the Roman Church now pretends to be a part of God's word, were delivered to us, by as univerſal uncontrolled Tradition as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is, we ſhould receive it as we do the Scripture.</p>
            <p>But it appears plainly that ſuch things were at firſt but private Opinions; which now are become the Doctrines of that particular Church: who would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her Decrees upon us under the Venerable Name of Apoſtolical Univerſal Tradition: which I have ſhewn you hath been an ancient cheat; and that we ought not to be ſo eaſie as to be deceived by it. But to be very wary, and afraid of truſting the Traditions of ſuch a Church, as hath not onely perverted ſome, aboliſhed others, and pretended them where there hath been none: but been a very unfaithfull preſerver of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63802:25"/>them and that in matters of great moment, where there were ſome; and <hi>laſtly</hi> warrants thoſe which it pretends to have kept, by nothing but its own infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. For which there is no
<hi>Tradition:</hi> but much againſt it; even in the Original
<hi>Tradition,</hi> the holy Scriptures: which plainly ſuppoſe the Roman Church may not onely err, but utterly ſail and be cut off from the Body of Chriſt: As they that pleaſe may reade, who will conſult the
<hi>Eleventh</hi> Chapter to the <hi>Romans, v.</hi> 20, 21, 22. Of which they are in the greater dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, becauſe they proudly claim ſo high a prerogative as that now mentioned; directly contrary to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Admonition in that place: <hi>be not high minded, but fear.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
            <p>I Shall end this Diſcourſe with a brief Admonition, relating to our Chriſtian practice.</p>
            <p>And what is there more proper or more ſeaſonable than this? While we reject all ſpurious Traditions, let us be ſure to keep cloſe to the genuine and true. Let us hold them faſt, and not let them go.</p>
            <p>Let us not diſpute our ſelves out of all Religion while we condemn that which is falſe: Nor break all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Diſcipline and Order; becauſe we cannot ſubmit to all humane impoſitions.</p>
            <p>In plain words, let us not throw off <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Papal Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ought to be the more carefull in obſerving the Divine Tradition delivered to us in the Scripture; and <pb n="50" facs="tcp:63802:26"/>according to the Scripture; becauſe we are not bound to other.</p>
            <p>While we contend againſt the <hi>half Communion;</hi> let us make a Conſcience to receive the <hi>whole</hi> frequently. It looks like Faction, rather than Religion, to be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt for that, which we mean not to uſe.</p>
            <p>In like manner, while we look upon additions to the Scripture, as vain; let us not neglect to reade and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe holy Writings.</p>
            <p>When we reject <hi>Purgatory</hi> as a fable; let us really dread Hell fire.</p>
            <p>And while we do not tye our ſelves to all uſages that have been in the Church, let us be carefull to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, <hi>firſt</hi> all the ſubſtantial duties of righteouſneſs, charity, ſobriety and godlineſs, which are unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably delivered to us by our Lord himſelf and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles: and <hi>ſecondly</hi> all the Ordinances of the Church wherein we live, which are not contrary to the word of God. For ſo hath the fame Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority delivered; that the people ſhould
<hi>obey</hi> thoſe that are their Guides and Governours;
<hi>ſubmitting</hi> themſelves to their authority; and avoiding all
<hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> with them, as moſt undecent in it ſelf, and pernicious to Religion; which ſuffers extremely, when neither <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Authority,</hi> nor <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> can end diſputes about Rites and Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Reade 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> V. 12. <hi>Heb.</hi> XIII. 17. 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> XI. 16. and reade ſuch places, as you ought to do all the other Scriptures, till your hearts be deeply affected with them.</p>
            <p>For be admoniſhed, in the laſt place, of this; which is of general uſe, and muſt never be forgotten: becauſe we ſhall loſe the benefit of that celeſtial Doctrine, which is delivered unto us, if we do not ſtrictly obſerve it. That <hi>as this Evangelical Doctrine is delivered down to <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63802:26"/>us, ſo we muſt be delivered up to it.</hi> Thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teaches us to ſpeak in VI. <hi>Rom.</hi> 17. where he thanks God that they who formerly had been ſervants of ſin, did now
<hi>obey from the heart that form of Doctrine, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which they were delivered.</hi> So the words run in the Greek (as the Margin of our Bibles inform you) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Tradition</hi> which we muſt be ſure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and hold faſt above all other; as that without which all our belief will be ineffectual.</p>
            <p>This is the very end for which all Divine Truth is delivered unto us, that we may be delivered and make a ſurrender of our ſelves unto it.</p>
            <p>Obſerve the force of the Apoſtles words: which tell us
<hi>firſt,</hi> that there was a certain form of Chriſtian Doctrine which the Apoſtles taught, compared here to a mould (ſo the word
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>form,</hi> may be tranſlated) into which metal or ſuch like matter is caſt; that it may receive the figure and ſhape of that mould.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now he compares the <hi>Roman</hi> Chriſtians to ſuch ductile, pliable matter: they being ſo delivered or caſt into this form or mould of Chriſtian Doctrine, that they were intirely framed and faſhioned according to it: and had all the lineaments, as I may ſay, of it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed upon their ſouls.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And having ſo received it, they were <hi>obedient</hi> to it: for without this, all the impreſſions, which by knowledge or faith were made upon their ſouls, were but an imperfect draught of what was intended in the Chriſtian Tradition.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And it was <hi>hearty</hi> obedience; ſincere compliance with the Divine will: ſuch obedience as became thoſe who underſtood their Religion to be a great deliverance and liberty from the ſlavery of ſin (before ſpoken of) into the happy freedom of the ſervice of God.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63802:27"/>
            <p n="5">5. All which <hi>laſtly</hi> he aſcribes to the grace of God, which had both delivered to them that Doctrine, and drawn them to deliver up themſelves to it; made their hearts ſoft and ductile to be caſt into that mould; and quickned them to Chriſtian Obedience; and given them a willing mind to obey chearfully. All this was from God's grace, and not their merits; and therefore the thanks was to be aſcribed to him, who ſucceeds and bleſſes all pious indeavours.</p>
            <p>Now according to this pattern, let us frame our ſelves: who, bleſſed be God, have a form of Doctrine delivered to us in this Church, exactly agreeable to the holy Scriptures: which lie open before us; and we are exhorted not onely to look into them, but we feel that grace which hath brought them to us, clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating that we ought to be formed according to the holy Doctrine therein delivered, by the delivery of our ſelves unto it. By the delivery of our mind, that is, to think of God, and our ſelves, and of our duty in every point, juſt as this inſtructs us. And by the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of our wills and affections, to be governed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated, according to its directions. And when we have conſented to this, we find the Divine grace repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to us the neceſſity of an hearty obedience, to what we know and believe and have embraced as the very Truth of God. To this we are continually drawn and mightily moved; and if we would ſhew our thankfulneſs for it, let us follow theſe godly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and conform our ſelves in all things to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly preſcriptions of this Book: being confident that if we do, we need not trouble our ſelves about any other model of Religion, which we find not here deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
            <p>For if you deſire to know what <hi>form of Doctrine</hi> it is, to which the Apoſtle would have us delivered; it <pb n="53" facs="tcp:63802:27"/>is certain it is a Doctrine directly oppoſite to all vice and wickedneſs. For herein the grace of God was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, he tells the <hi>Romans,</hi> in that it had brought them, from being ſlaves of ſin, heartily to obey the Chriſtian Doctrine: which taught, that is, vertue and piety.</p>
            <p>Now to this the preſent Romaniſts can pretend to add nothing. All the parts of a godly life are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently taught us, in the holy Scriptures. And if we would ſeriouſly practiſe and follow this Doctrine, from the very heart; we ſhould eaſily ſee there is no other but what is there delivered. For whatſoever is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be neceſſary beſides, is not <hi>a Doctrine according unto godlineſs</hi> (as the Apoſtle calls Chriſtianity) but the very deſign of it is to open an eaſier way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than that laid before us in the holy Scriptures; by <hi>Maſſes for the dead,</hi> by <hi>Indulgences,</hi> by <hi>Satisfactions,</hi> and the
<hi>merits of the Saints,</hi> and ſeveral other ſuch like inventions: which have no foundation in the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</hi> nor in true
<hi>Antiquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is a word indeed which is very much preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<hi>Antiquity</hi> they ſay is on their ſide; but it is nothing different from what hath been ſaid about <hi>Tradition.</hi> And if we will run up to the true <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> there is nothing ſo ancient as the <hi>holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> They are the oldeſt Records of Religion: and by them if we frame our lives, we are ſure it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the moſt authentick and ancient directions of piety, delivered in the holy Oracles of God. So both ſides confeſs them to be. And if the old Rule be ſafe, <hi>that is true, which is firſt,</hi> we are ſafe-enough: for there is nothing
<hi>before</hi> this to be our Guide; and there can be nothing <hi>after</hi> this, but muſt be tried by it. According to another Rule, as old as reaſon it <pb n="54" facs="tcp:63802:28"/>ſelf; <hi>the firſt in every kind, is the meaſure of all the reſt.</hi> And, as ſure as that there is a Goſpel of God's grace, <hi>they that walk after this Rule</hi> (this Divine <hi>Canon) peace ſhall be upon them, and mercy;</hi> they being the true <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or Church, <hi>of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:63802:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Fincham Gardiner.</head>
            <p>AContinuation and Vindication of the Defence of Dr.
<hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Unreaſonableneſs of Separation, in Anſwer to Mr.
<hi>Baxter,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lob,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Conſiderations of preſent uſe, conſidering the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Reſulting from the Change of our Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Perſwaſive to Communion with the Church of
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Reſolution of ſome Caſes of Conſcience, which Reſpect Church-Communion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Caſe of Indifferent things, uſed in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, Propoſed and Stated by conſidering theſe Queſtions,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. A Diſcourſe about Edification.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Reſolution of this Caſe of Conſcience,
<hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church of</hi> England<hi>'s Symbolizing ſo far as it doth with the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>makes it unlawfull to hold Communion with the Church of</hi> England?</p>
            <p n="6">6. A Letter to <hi>Anonymus,</hi> in Anſwer to his Three Letters to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> about Church-Communion.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Certain Caſes of Conſcience reſolved, concerning the Lawfulneſs of joyning with Forms of Prayer in Publick Worſhip. In two Parts.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Caſe of Mixt Communion. Whether it be Lawfull to ſeparate from a Church upon the Account of promiſcuous Congregations, and Mixt Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63802:29"/>
            <p n="9">9. An Anſwer to the Diſſenters Objections againſt the Common Prayers, and ſome other Parts of Divine Service Preſcribed in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. The Caſe of Kneeling at the Holy Sacrament, Stated and Reſolved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The firſt Part.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Certain Caſes of Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Second Part.</p>
            <p n="12">12. A Diſcourſe of Profiting by Sermons, and of going to hear where Men think they can profit moſt.</p>
            <p n="13">13. A Diſcourſe about the charge of Novelty upon the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> made by the Papiſts asking of us the Queſtion, Where was our Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luther?</hi> Printed for
<hi>Robert Horne</hi> at the South Entrance of the Royal Exchange.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
